大家早安
The four books of the gospel Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John
在師父音書中 馬太 馬可 路加 約翰
They tell of the life of our Lord Jesus Christ
他們都講述了耶穌的生平
In essence, the life of our Lord Jesus Christ
is the object lesson that teaches us about God
其實 耶穌的生平就是一個實質的教導
關於神的一生
He is the Word who became flesh
祂就是道 成了肉身
The Word is Jesus
而這道就是耶穌
and Jesus Himself is the Living Word
祂就是那個生命
The Word that we preach and read and hear
is more than a simple study of literature
我們所講 所聽 所讀的聖經裡面的話語
不單只是文字
It is more than evidence that validates history
祂也是一個見證歷史 不單只是一個見證歷史的證據
也不是單單是解說神學的一些的證據
The Word demands our attention to God's voice
這個道需要我們真的去專心 專注在神的聲音上
and therefore it requires us to respond
it requires a response from man's heart
而且真的需要我們人從心裡面的去回應
The story from the passage we read earlier of the rich young man
is found in three of the four Gospel books
剛才我們所唸的經文呢
在詩福音裡面有三個福音書記載著
Three times
三次
We learn that repetition in scripture reinforces the emphasis of its intent meaning
我們知道如果有幾次的加重的去疏縮的時候呢
我們就知道它的意義特別的重要
Heaven recorded three times by three different writers
The story of the rich young man amplifies God's desire for us to examine our motives
as believers in these modern times
而這個故事呢 真的神也是要在這個世代
特別的去告訴我們這裡面所藏在的意義
What does it mean to be a Christian?
做一個基督徒有什麼意義呢
Who should Christians follow?
我們基督徒是跟從誰呢
How should Christians live?
我們基督徒要如何的去生活
What does being a Christian mean?
Who should Christians follow?
And how should Christians live?
我們要如何的去做 如何的去跟隨
我們真的知道我們是去聽誰的話語
Let us pray
我們低頭禱告
Emily, Father, may we experience your presence in our gathering this morning
天父 願我們真的感覺到你與我們同在
Father, may your spirit arouse ours as we listen to your word
願你的靈來激勵我們當我們在聽你的話語的時候
And may your love fill this space as we worship the name above all names
願你的靈 你的愛充滿這個地方 讓我們真的來一起的送贈你的名
The name of our Lord Jesus Christ
也來送贈我們耶穌基督的名
Our Master, our King, and our Savior
我們的主 我們的神
And in His name we all pray
我們奉主的名禱告
And the church says Amen
在這個經文之前 我們就看到耶穌跟一般的孩子在一起
祂跟他們一起玩
祂擁抱他們
祂也跟他們一起唱歌 一起的歡笑
或者祂也跟他們跳舞吧
這時候祂沒有教導他們
也沒有訓話他們
也沒有在指責他們
而在父母還有一些成人的圍觀之下
耶穌好像就變回了一個小孩一樣
我們看到耶穌和孩童之間有一個很特別的關係
因為他們之間的互動是非常溫暖的
看到他們有這麼的歡樂 好像耶穌在舉行一個假期的聖經學校一般
祂也沒有告訴父母說 你們可以去做你們的事 我來照顧你們的孩子
因為耶穌並不是這樣的
因為耶穌要教導成人們 他們帶著孩童的眼光去看祂
我們真的需要去學習怎樣把我們的孩子介紹給神
也讓神來認識他們
第一
Keep an open mind and an open heart as you welcome children into the presence of the Lord
當我們把孩子帶到神的同在的時候
我們自己本身就有一個開放的思想和心靈
你希望耶穌怎麼對待你的孩子呢
你希望祂能接受他們
你希望祂能夠聆聽他們
跟他們有一個同樣的心智
耶穌的溫柔慈愛就是我們現在小孩們的需要
第二
Give children permission to be who they are
so that they may discover the person of the Lord
我們要給小孩一個他們適合的環境
讓他們與神之間能夠去產生一個彼此的關係
耶穌是一個很關懷人
是一個很慈愛的
也是一個很饒恕人的
所以對我們小孩的身心靈的發展都是很重要的
第三
Show grace so that our children may learn and know the promise of our Lord
我們真的要把恩典彰顯出來
因為讓我們的小孩能夠知道神的應許
耶穌擁抱他們
把手按在他們的頭上
祂祝福他們
我們要記得恩典不只是一次性的
我們要把恩典彰顯出來的時候
就是要繼續地為我們的孩子禱告
也要去愛他們
因為我們知道耶穌從來沒有放棄我們
我們也不要放棄我們的孩子
然後耶穌轉頭向成人們說
讓他們來到我面前
不要禁止他們
and you must also be like them in order to receive the kingdom of God
而且你們自己也要學像孩子一樣
那麼你們才能夠承受神的國
What a sobering lesson
所以這是一個很驚醒的學習
Something to keep in mind as we evaluate our own children's ministry
當我們看我們自己兒童的施工的時候
對我們來說也是一個很驚醒的學習
Let's pray that the Lord may give us wisdom
願我們禱告我們神能夠賜給我們智慧
May God help us not to be a hindrance
讓我們自己本身也不要成為一個阻礙
Because you see it's not only the responsibility of the Sunday school teachers
而且我們知道這不單只是足了學老師的責任
As parents, it's your responsibility as well
做父母這個也是我們的責任
We all have a part in our children's ministry
我們每一個人在兒童施工裡面都是一份子
Whether at church, at home, or at the restaurant
就算在餐館裡面
Don't forbid your children to come to me, Jesus says
耶穌說不要禁止你的孩子來到我的面前
You are their parents
你是他們的父母
但是他們是神的兒女
Now we come to our text this morning, our passage
現在我們就來到今天我們剛才讀的經文上
A young man ran so fast
pushes his way through the crowd and falls before Jesus
我們看到這個年輕人跑得很快
然後他就來到耶穌面前跪在他的面前
Sir, you don't know who I am
But I have something very important that I need an answer to
他說 哦 良聖的父子啊
雖然你不認識我
但是呢 我很確實的需要一個答案
Continuing, he said
Good teacher, I know you are a very busy man
So I will be quick
然後他也說 哎呀 父子我知道你很忙
所以我會很快的把事情說了
Doesn't that sound very much like us?
這聽起來是不是很像我們呢
Everything we want, we want it quick
很多時候我們要一些事情我們要很快的就得到
So he cuts to the chase
所以他很快的就來到他所要說的
What must I do to have eternal life?
他說 我當做什麼才能夠承受永生呢
Oh, everyone in the crowd
They hear the question and they agree with the question
在群眾裡面呢 當然他們聽到這個問題的時候
他們也需要去知道這個答案
Everyone wants to know, but no one dares to ask
很多人都想知道 但是他們不敢去問
Even the Pharisees who have challenged Jesus earlier
are eager to hear what Jesus has to say
那些曾經挑戰耶穌的法利薩人
相信他們也在等著那個答案吧
People who once did not care about heaven and hell
suddenly are interested
那些呢 從來不關懷什麼是天堂 什麼是地獄的
相信這時候他們也有興趣知道
Wow, even Jesus' own disciples
waited for their teacher's answer
我相信當時門徒們呢 也在等著耶穌的答案
It was a great question
這是一個很好的問題
It reminds me of the story of a married couple
這個就讓我想起有一個故事關於一個夫婦
They are both about 60 years old
他們兩個大概都60歲了
And they are celebrating their 35th anniversary
他們在慶祝他們35週年的紀念
And during their party
然後在他們的慶祝會上的時候
A genie appeared to congratulate them
and to grant them each one wish
有一個精靈出現
然後呢 就對他們夫婦說
我會給你們每一個人一個願望
The wife wanted to travel the world
這個妻子呢 就很想去環遊世界
So the genie waved the wand and poof!
wife has tickets in her hand for a world cruise
然後這精靈就揮棒
然後呢 那個妻子的手中就有一張
環遊世界的輪船
Next
The genie asked the husband what he wanted
然後這個精靈就問他的丈夫
啊 你需要什麼呢
The 60-year-old man who loves his wife said
這個很愛他妻子的60歲的老公就說
I wish I have a wife 30 years younger than me
我希望有一個比我年輕30歲的妻子
So genie picked the wand and poof!
然後這個精靈呢 也把棒子一揮
The husband is 90 years old
那這個丈夫就變成90歲了
The young man had a great question
剛才那個年輕人他有一個很好的問題
The problem is we know what we want
but we often don't know what we are asking
很多時候我們知道我們要什麼
但是我們不知道自己在問什麼
What must I do? What must I accomplish
in order to acquire eternal life?
他所注重的是 我可以做什麼
才能夠承受永生
We must follow the one who is good
我們必須要跟隨那個良善的
Jesus says why do you call me good?
耶穌問他說 你為什麼稱我是良善的
Let me ask you why do you call Jesus good?
我要問你們 你們為什麼覺得
耶穌是好的 是良善的呢
Why do you say that this whole church thing is good?
為什麼你說來到教會裡面
好多事情都是好的呢
To human beings, something is good
if it is agreeable, if it is favorable
and if it is satisfying, it's good
對我們人來說的話呢
好的事情就是符合我們的要求
是我們希望要的 也能夠滿足我們的
First class on an airplane is good
飛機的頭等艙是好的
A+ on a test is good
考試拿到A+是好的
Cold air on a hot day is good
然後在一個熱天的時候
有一陣涼風是好的
Good is invariably a positive return
that meets our approval
而這個好呢 就好像是經過我們的同意
然後有一個很好的回報
The goodness of God is His Holiness
但是神的好呢 是祂的聖潔
His perfection 祂的完美
and His sovereignty 還有祂的至高無上
Good in God is absolute excellence
好在對神來說是真的沒有什麼可比
是真的在高高之上的
Good by man standard is simply emotions
and experience that drives our ambition
人的好呢 只是因為我們的情緒
我們的需要 我們的目的
讓我們真的向著這個志向去追求
但是這個都是有限的
Do you know who Jesus is?
你知道耶穌是誰嗎?
See the young man sees Jesus merely as an agent
rather the answer
我覺得這個年輕人呢 看耶穌呢
就是一個代言人
但是他沒有真正的注重在那個答案上面
That's because he was only interested in his own benefit
因為他所注重的是自身的那個需要
He was looking and searching to bridge his fortune on earth
while living to extend his prosperity into eternal life
He doesn't want to lose his earthly treasure
He wants to build on
so that he can bring it with him to eternal life
他其實就是想保住他現在在世的這些財富
然後要有一個保障
能把這些財富繼續的在他死亡之後能難的存在
Let that not be our mistake
Only God is truly good
and because he is good
he knows what's best for us
因為只有神是那位良善那位好的
而且他很清楚的知道什麼對我們是最好的
We must follow the one who is good
And two, we must follow the one who is righteous
Eternal life is not something anyone can do to earn
永生不是我們可以去賺取的
But our earthly training when we go to school, when we go to work
it tells us that there is a cause
and there is an effect in how this world operates
但是當我們去上學或者去上班的時候
這個世界的一個定論就是告訴我們
你做的什麼你就會得到什麼
You do this, you get that
你做這個,你就得到那個
But no amount of things that we do
equate to the sacrifice of our Lord Jesus Christ
但是無論我們做什麼呢
都不能夠跟耶穌的犧牲相等
It is only through the shedding of his blood
and the breaking of his body
can we as sinners be reconciled to God
接著耶穌的保血和他破碎的身體呢
我們才能夠與神和好
Salvation is not acquired by any means or any effort
真的,救恩不能夠通過我們做的一些事情
或者是去行的一些事情所得到
It must begin with obedience to the one who is righteous
而是必須向那位公義的信號順服
And it is interesting that Jesus answered
with something that the young man was very familiar with
而且我們也覺得很奇怪
耶穌用了這個年輕人所知道的
一些的問題來回答他
Jesus quoted the second half of the Ten Commandments
耶穌用了十誡中的後五誡來回答他
Don't commit adultery, do not kill, do not murder
Do not steal, do not bear false witness, do not cheat
But honor your mother and honor your father
他告訴他不可殺人,不可奸淫
不可偷盜,不可做假見證
不可恢復人,但是當孝敬父母
You know what I thought was interesting
When Jesus was with the children
He did not tell the children any of this
But he tells the young man, us brothers and sisters
Second half of the Ten Commandments
And honor your mother and father
我很奇怪,就是耶穌在跟孩子在一起的時候
他並沒有告訴他們這些
但是他告訴年輕人這些
而且特別注重在要孝敬父母
The first five Ten Commandments
pertain to our relationship with God
實際的前五階呢是我們跟神的關係
The second half has to do with our relationship with other people
但是後五階呢確實告訴我們我們與人的關係
You see the young man was a ruler of people
我們知道這個年輕人是一個領導
He is an authority over people
他也是去管理人的
He is a representative of people
他也是代表人民的
And this is his reply
這個就是他的回答
Teacher, all these I have observed from my youth
I have been a good boy
他跟他耶穌說
夫子這一切我從小就做了
都遵守了
I have complied
我已經做完了
I have not been bad
我沒有做壞事
I have been very good
我是一個很好的人
Parents, it is wonderful to teach our children to be good
很好
如果你教你的孩子去做好的是很好的事情
It is awesome to want our children to behave
to work hard
to study
to do all the things well
要我們的孩子有一個好的表現
去努力
去做一些很好的事情
一切都是很好很美好的
But being good is only half the prize
但是做好的就是只是一半的獎賞
The other half is truth
但是另一半就是要去懂得真理
Do we teach our children the truth?
我們有沒有教導孩子真理
Good is by having confidence in self
好是因為我們對自己有自信
Truth is having faith in Christ
但是真理就是我們對神有信心
Knowing Jesus is only half the joy
我們認識神只是一半的喜樂
But doing His will completes your blessing
但是我們如果能夠去遵守他給我們的旨意
我們就把一切都完成了
You know what Jesus gave him?
你知道耶穌給他什麼嗎
Jesus looked at him
and he gave the man what he was missing
他就給這個年輕人所錯失的
Jesus loved him
耶穌愛他
The story of the rich young man
as I said earlier
appears in three of the four gospel books
我們知道這個年輕人的故事
在世福音當中有三個福音在記載
But only in Mark was it noted
that Jesus looked at him
at the young man and loved him
但只是在馬可福音裡面
我們可以看到耶穌寫著
這個書裡面寫著
耶穌看著他就愛他
Mark couldn't have been the better person
to write such a profound caption about Jesus
馬可真的是寫這個句子的最好人選
See Mark was not one of the twelve disciples
因為我們知道馬可不是十二門徒裡面的一位
In fact his faith was in and out, up and down
我們知道他的信心也是上上下下起起伏伏的
But to be so moved upon seeing the true character of Jesus
it was important that Mark wrote this down
但是當他在那邊看到神的真心情的時候呢
他真的要把這個動作寫下來
And he thought it was important that others might read it
and know the love of Jesus Christ
而且他也覺得這是很重要的
把這一個記錄下來
讓別人也能夠看到耶穌的愛
In our relationship with brothers and sisters
我們與弟兄姊妹之間的關係
We must be more Christ-like in the way we love one another
當我們彼此相愛的時候
我們真的要特別的學上
How Jesus can just love people with such pure conviction
such deep compassion
and with such authentic affection
is something we all must learn
我們真的看到耶穌真的是很純粹的去愛人
而且他有很深的側眼的心去愛別人
We are sinners
我們都是罪人
We are broken people
But in Christ His love covers all of our shortcomings
但是在基督裡面呢
他的愛把我們的一切缺點都遮蓋了
We are to share the love that we have received from our Lord
我們真的要去分享我們從神得來的愛
Last month our youth helped raise funds
for the Thailand missions
上個月我們的年輕人他們為泰國的事情來籌款
Last week our children assembled 155 boxes
to share with other children
上個星期我們的兒童們也裝了155個鞋盒
去與其他的小孩子分享
Our church is getting ready to support the missions in Bangladesh
而且我們教會也在準備去支持孟加拉的一些的宣教
Maybe even Japan
或者更遠的是日本
We share as a church
because others have given so we may also have
因為我們去分享是因為別人所給我們
我們也能夠去分享給別人
We love because Christ loved us first
我們去愛也是因為神先愛我們
We must follow the one who is life
我們也必須跟隨那是生命的
Jesus knows where the young man has been
and where the young man is heading
耶穌知道這個年輕人是從哪裡來的
他現在也是在這往哪裡去
So like a good doctor
Jesus gave him the young man's prognosis
而成為一個好的醫生
他也給這個年輕人一個診斷
One thing you lack in life
你還缺少一件
And Jesus tells him three things that he must first do
而且耶穌也告訴他有三樣事情他必須先做
Go, sell and give
你要去賣然後要去給
Why go?
為什麼要去呢
Because when we go we look back at our traveled past
因為當我們去的時候
我們看到我們以前所發生的一些事情
It is a chance that Jesus is giving us
to change and to repent
這個是耶穌給我們一個去改變
去悔改的機會
Why sell?
你為什麼要去變賣呢
To permanently let go of the things that control us
Why give?
To share with others what God has blessed us
But see, many people see this as a problem
We see ourselves as fish in water
and the water is being taken away from us
我們會感覺到我們是在水中的魚
但是我們的水被別人拿走了
But actually we are like fish being set free from the bowl
into the ocean of endless opportunities
但是其實我們就是一隻被放進大海的一隻魚
而且有很多很多的機會
And Jesus didn't just say give everything away
耶穌也不單只是說把一切都給出去吧
Instead, Jesus tells him to give to the poor
而且耶穌叫他要去給窮人
Even though material possessions mean nothing to God
雖然物質的事情對神來說是沒有什麼意義的
Our God is not a wasteful God
但是祂也不是一個浪費的耶穌
He is the way, the truth, and the life
祂是真理,道路,生命
最後一點
We must follow the one who is Lord
我們必須跟隨那位是主的
Finally, Jesus said this to him
最後呢,耶穌跟他說
And then you come and follow me
你還要來跟從我
Now, it is not mentioned in this passage
But I am sure brothers and sisters are very familiar
That when Jesus usually say come and follow me
It involves taking up your cross
雖然在這個經文裡面沒有記載
但是很多時候當我們聽到耶穌說
來跟從我的時候呢
通常都會跟著要背棄你的屍駕
It is commonly known as the cost of discipleship
而且呢這個就是好像一個作為信徒的一個要做的事情
I think it is more of a reward than a cost
但是呢我覺得這個對我們來說其實是一個獎賞
而不是一個代價
Following Jesus only means that God is going to be with you everywhere you go
而且呢這個代表著無論我們到哪裡去
神都會跟我們同在
But we must accept His invitation
但是我們首先要接受祂的邀請
We must be willing to take up our own cross
我們必須背棄我們自己的屍駕
We must deny our self
Put our old self behind
and follow Him
The Bible doesn't tell us what happened to the young man
聖經沒有告訴我們後來這個年輕人怎麼樣了
But he was sad
He walked away sorrowfully
because he had great possessions
He was a good man
He kept all the laws
He honored his parents
He made a good living
He even came face to face with Jesus Christ the superstar
而且呢他也跟耶穌面對面了
But that fish stayed in its bowl
但是這隻魚呢卻在他的魚缸裡面
His wealth, his fame, his treasures
They were his master
他的財產,他的名聲都成為了他的主人
We must follow the one who is good and righteous
我們必須跟隨那個良善,那個公義的
We must follow the one who is love and life
我們也必須跟隨那個有愛,有生命的
We must follow the one who is Lord
而且我們也必須跟隨那個主
Don't just come when you need something
不要只是單單你需要什麼的時候才來
Jesus says come and follow me
耶穌跟他說你來跟從我
Don't just come to take care whatever you need to take care of
不要只是來來解決你一切的需要
Jesus says take up your cross, then come and follow me
耶穌說背起你的支架,來跟從我
Let me conclude by sharing a prayer by someone
after reading the story of the rich young man
我要分享一個就是一個人
他看完這個年輕人的故事之後
一個的禱告
So this is this man's prayer after reading this story
所以這個是這個人的一個禱告
當他唸完這個經文之後
He says dear Lord
I've been reading and rereading the record of the rich young ruler
and his obvious wrong choices
我持續的在唸這一段的經文
然後我就看到這個年輕人的一些錯誤的選擇
But it has set me thinking Lord
但是呢這就讓我再一次的去思考
No matter how much wealth this young man had
不論這個年輕人是多麼的富有
He could not ride in a car
當時的他不能夠去駕著一輛車
Remember this is a story from 2000 plus years ago
因為這個故事是記載在2000多年前了
And he cannot have surgery when he wants to
or when he needs to
當他有生病或者什麼事情的時候
他也不能夠去做手術
He cannot turn on the light
他也不能夠去打開電燈
There's no electricity then
因為那時候並沒有電
He cannot buy important medicine like penicillin
He cannot buy penicillin
他也不能夠去買那些很重要的藥物
比如盤尼斯林
He cannot hear the grand piano
他也聽不到鋼琴的聲音
He cannot watch TV
也看不到電視
He cannot wash dishes in running water
他也不能夠用自來水去洗碗
He cannot type a letter or send an email
他也不能夠去發電郵或者是去打一封信
He cannot mow the lawn
他也不能夠去用除草機去除草
He cannot fly in an airplane
他也不能夠去駕一輛飛機
He cannot sleep on an innerspring mattress
他也不能夠睡在彈簧床上
He cannot even go on the internet or talk on the phone
他也不能夠上網或者是通電話
So Lord, if this young man was rich
如果這個年輕人是這麼的富有
Then what am I?
那我又怎麼樣呢?
What I think he is saying is
我想他是這樣講的
We can have anything and we can have everything
But if we do not have the Lord
No matter how rich or loaded you are
You have nothing
因為無論我們是多麼的富有
我們擁有什麼的東西
很多很多的物件
但是呢如果我們沒有神
我們什麼都不是
So when you say grace at the dinner table this Thanksgiving
所以當今年你在感恩桌上做這個禱告的時候
Remember everything is the Lord's provision
要記得這一切都是從神而來的
And after the dishes are done
Yes, don't forget you still have to do dishes
而且呢吃完飯之後要把碗洗了
And your children or your family go to bed
那你的孩子要去睡覺了
Ask yourself this question
你要問自己這個問題
Who am I following?
你跟從誰?
你跟從誰呢?
May the peace of the Lord be with all of you
願神的祝福與你們同在
Amen